A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Latin America and the Caribbean, Bogota Field Office Files on Venezuela FA560
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Latin America and the Caribbean, Bogota Field Office Files on Venezuela
1962-1971
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA560
1.4 Cubic Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Alphabetical
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
Ford Foundation activities in Venezuela in the 1960s.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation originally maintained an office in Bogota, Colombia from 1962 to 1982. After the Bogota office's closure in 1982, responsibility for Colombia programming was administered by other Latin American country offices focusing on the Andean Region and Southern Cone until 2016 when the Foundation established another office in Bogota.
The Ford Foundation started to explore possibilities for assisting programs in Colombia in 1960 in response to requests from Colombian universities. It made its first grants to the country in 1961, and then, in 1962, it established an office in Bogota. During the time of the first Bogota office, the Foundation's Colombia program primarily focused on supporting projects and initiatives involved with education, social sciences, science and technology, agriculture, and population. Within the first 14 years of the Colombia program's existence, the Foundation had spent almost $20.6 million in grants to the country (The Ford Foundation in Colombia, 1961-1974, Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 9287-11774 (FA739D), Report 009501). At different times throughout its run, the first Bogota office was also responsible for administering the Foundation's Peru and Venezuela programs. It oversaw grants for both countries until 1965 when the Lima, Peru office was established and the Mexico City, Mexico office took over responsibility for the Venezuela program. The Bogota office resumed responsibility for the Venezuela program in 1972 after the Foundation closed its Caracas, Venezuela office.
The Ford Foundation closed the Bogota office in 1982. Regional responsibility for the Andean Region and Southern Cone was transferred to the Lima office. The Lima office administered the Foundation's Colombia program until 1991 when the Foundation then established the Andean Region and Southern Cone office in Santiago, Chile (The Ford Foundation: 40 Years in the Andean Region and Southern Cone, 2003, Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 13949-17726 (FA739F), Report 016928). The Santiago office oversaw the Foundation's support for Colombia until the Foundation opened a new Bogota office in 2016.
The current Andean Region office in Bogota oversees programming in Colombia and Peru.
Biographical / Historical
In 1962, the Ford Foundation sent a survey team to Venezuela for the purposes of investigating if and how the Foundation could support development in the country. The Foundation established its Venezuela program based on the recommendations of this team. Initially, support for Venezuela was managed out of the Foundation's Bogota, Colombia office. Then, in 1965, the Foundation moved its Venezuela program to its Mexico City, Mexico office as part of a Mexico/Central America/Venezuela focus. The Foundation set up an independent Caracas office in 1966, and Venezuela related grants were administered by this office until its closure in 1972 (Future Status of the Venezuelan Office memo from Roy Crawley to Harry Wilhelm, September 24, 1967, Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 6262-9286 (FA739C), Report 008961). Although the Foundation reduced its funding for Venezuela projects, it continued its Venezuela program through its Bogota office (Your Colombia Visit memo from James Himes to David Bell and William Carmichael, July 3, 1973, Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 13949-17726 (FA739F), Report 015406).
The Foundation's Venezuela program chiefly focused on supporting initiatives and projects involved with agriculture, education, population, science and technology, and social sciences within the country.
- Abate, Dr. John de, 1970 (Box 1)
- Asociacion Civil pro Clubes y Amas de Casa, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
- Carabobo University, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
- Corporacion Venezolana de Guyana, 1962-1968 (Box 1)
- Faculties of Economics in Venezuela Trip Report, 1962 (Box 1)
- Ford Foundation Involvement in Science and Technology in Venezuela, 1965 (Box 1)
- Ford Foundation -- Seven Years in Venezuela, 1962-1969 (Box 1)
- Fundacion Creole, 1963-1972 (Box 1)
- Fundacion la Salle de Ciencia Naturales, 1962-1971 (Box 1)
- Fundacion Mendoza, 1962-1970 (Box 1)
- Indiana University of the Catolica-Indiana Universities Economics Program -- First Annual Report, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
- Informe que Presentas la Facultad de Ciencias U.C.V. a la Fundacion Ford, 1967 (Box 1)
- Mass Communication Projects, 1970 (Box 1)
- Organization of American States, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
- Overseas Education Fund, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
- Universidad Catolica Andres Bello -- Evaluation of Economics Program, 1965 October 9-12 (Box 1)
- Venezuela Ecology, 1970 (Box 1)
- Wilbur, K.M., 1969 (Box 1)